foreign
comes as a result of correctly
developed virtue Sila samadhi paneer
um and and that's their difference like
do do there's a person who is keeping
the presets
do they allow that pressure to arise
and by that I don't even go and seek out
things no you start polluted so when you
start putting on
like the breaks on your behavior and
sense restraint and so on the things
will start coming up
so when those things come up
are you allowing them
to manifest or immediately grip by
craving or getting rid of them
and doubling down in your behavior
doubling down in whatever observances
you do that's why you're not keeping
places right and that's why you're not
Discerning you will not be Discerning
where samadhi actually is and that's
exactly why that type of attitude of I
must get there is naturally leads to
that nature somebody that we often talk
about where you're just just focusing on
on an object of so in order to shut
everything else down mechanical
mechanical exactly it's the extension of
already mechanically kept precepts and
Behavior now it's just the mechanical
methods and and routines so that there
is no room for your mind to sort of move
and turn around and look at itself
and the whole idea of meditation is just
borderline like you know being asleep
and switched off all the time yet at the
same time expecting some great
Revelation or pleasure to come from it
and we said that before for as long as
you're meditating out of that craving of
having not resolved the things the
pressure you pay for your meditation
um you are meditating with sensuality
Miss meditated over premeditated his own
in that other suit that compares it to a
jackalazone but that is another sort of
the Buddha Compares it to a stupid horse
that just looks at hey hey give me hey
give me give me the pleasure of reward
and he does not consider what the
trainer will make him do that day it's
going to be whipped this is going to
result in this so no all he sees is the
pleasure of the food that's it I'm just
concentrating on Hay nothing else exists
according to the modern standards there
will be a very successful meditation
that's a dumb stupid horse that's not a
thoroughbred the hosted actually successful is the
the hosted actually successful is the
one that sure he has a tendency to the
pleasure still but he recognized weight
I will not focus on the reward I will
not narrow my perspective on just one
point of satisfaction I will think about
where is the trainer what is he up to
what is he going to make me do
if I look this way he makes me do this
if I look that way he makes me do that
and start to discern these signs of
basically mind development
and they all come see the wisdom of that
horse comes on account of orderly having
taken the Virgin census string rightly
so when hindrance is manifest
you attend to them rightly you don't
replace them with something else
and that's already with that's already
uh unraveling all the wrong most of the
wrong views and oceans and perceptions
and so on and certainly it's revealing
the nature of sensuality the nature of
the the unpleasantness of your will the
Peril of Destruction and so on
I actually think it would be
very unlikely or pretty much impossible
for somebody to take that virtue rightly
in that way that you've just described
without um
um
actively or willingly be willing to
question your views yeah we have lots of
instructions
because the views naturally and it's not
accidental it supports that type of
wrong view of whatsoever yes there's
really the right criteria for what is
what is why you would why you would act
virtuously or like some God or something
some kind of idea of what is like
external idea of what is good and what
is bad but equally like the idea this
if there's a you know a bad thought or a
bad mental state I must yeah I must get
rid of it whatever is
and see that so again like you would you
be why would you be trying to get rid of
something that doesn't belong to you and
it wasn't you doing exactly so by taking
it at face value then I must get rid of
this you're taking the ownership of the
mind that doesn't belong to you at face
value and that's the thing and also if you're
and that's the thing and also if you're
not seeing your mind to begin with if
you're focused on getting rid of the
thoughts that are bothering you you're
failing to see that these thoughts are
the result of the mental state
underneath because you're too concerned to deal
because you're too concerned to deal
with them you're not you're not even
going to see that mind let alone its
signs and so on so that's the whole
point we just keep hammering in through
precepts and enduring things on the
right level
you recognize wait these thoughts are
abate it's the mental state that they result
it's the mental state that they result
from it's the state of mind
we change the earth like this which has
this characteristic simply by not acting
out you're already closer to see that
wild animal for what it is and then it's
like okay so
thoughts or not this type of that type
there the the Revelation the symptom
they're the indicators of the problem of
the mental state do I see that mental
state enduring or am I just again
falling back onto oh let me just deal
with these thoughts let me just indulge
them or get rid of them
either way you fail to see the mind and
by not saying the Mind How Can you tame
it how can you train it how can develop
it
so you're still on the level of fully
absorbing hay and reward of the food and
the taste and senses perverting the
order of the oldest perverses you're
you're not succeeding in unpivoting it
basically yeah I am doing it yeah
but if you don't act out of that
pressure yeah that's again like whoever
whoever has been trapped like by bait or
by an addiction
is because they couldn't give up that
that that momentary
satisfaction of following along the the
given action and so on or let me let me
just grab this let me just take it I'll
deal with consequences later that's the
middle of it again so it is so yes it
has to that that pain that you're going
to feel has to be there initially just
to the extent that you refrain from
falling jumping back into the Trap or
biting onto a bait
but with with basic wisdom with with one
with thumbnail basically with thunder
reflection of frequently reflecting upon
yeah okay it's painful but I do
factually know that this is a bait that
this is a trap I've seen it so many
times so
so
either way I'll suffer
let me at least now suffer in a
different way that has potential
for me completely losing desire towards
any bait any any pleasure that would
want to entice me
so that's how Sila develops somebody
that then develops spania they're not
separate things you do one after the
other um and there's certainly obviously not
um and there's certainly obviously not
mechanical things you do either if they
are mechanical then they become separate
and then yeah yes if you're doing it
mechanically you're not doing them yeah
exactly that's that's not where the
restaurants that's how it's mud is yeah
abstract right yeah yeah exactly
divorced from from the actual experience
yeah [Music]
[Music]
and then you can yeah get into religious
Doctrine and yeah proliferate into
academic well that's that's what they've
done or probably a number of other students
or probably a number of other students
say the uh you know somebody might be
living withdrawn from sincerity but they
are not doing it rightly
they're not developing their mind
correctly on account of it you know
they're still they're still adhering to
that virtue even celibacy and everything
else externally out of some you know
Faith or tradition or Superstition or
whatever well because again
well because again
um it's not allowed to enter on to that
right level because that's too
unpleasant to bear too close to home to
bear so it's projected over there but
they're going to result in them yeah you
might not go like if you're part of
determination you might adhere to this
keeping these presets for the rest of
your life you know blindly but doesn't
matter um well that will then result into uh
um well that will then result into uh
increasing of your views and so it says
like they do live withdrawn from sensuality
they do live withdrawn from sensuality
from these baits they say no to them
they have the ones that go a bit too far
then once they come they don't go too
far but then they start
holding views start proliferating views
it's always described on the level of or
the world is eternal the world is not
those are like generic categories
whatever you boil down to practically
obviously you know suitors don't speak
in this you know template block
categories so you don't necessarily
always have specific details well
practically uh what accumulation of the
views on account of living withdrawn
from centrality will manifest is
basically intensifying of day-to-day
views and opinions and stances on
everything mundane
literally it's not about the
universities like this you know now
we're getting a better argument and I
got a no no but people would get in a
better argument on account of I don't
think monks should have their fingers
crossed like that
well what source your code for that and
people who start basically falling out
and then pulling Rank and he introducing
the whole hierarchical institution of I
tell everybody what to do because I'm
the most senior here and you gotta obey
to me like an army military command
chain of command basically and all of
that is because even these mundane
little things how you walk how you put
the cloth down how do you cross your
fingers become very intensified and become very
become very intensified and become very
important for me and I am moved and I'm
troubled by that that someone else does
although it's in and of itself
completely ridiculous there's nothing to
do with it mind will not let go of it
because you deprived it of the the main
source of escape from the unpleasant
feeling which is Pleasures so then it's
going to be finding Pleasures in these
other subtlet things yeah for as long as you
subtlet things yeah for as long as you
either don't actually take up the virtue
correctly and for that you will not have
to go back to the start yeah because
yeah this is the opposite of composure
again yeah yeah exactly exactly
[Music] type of enduring but also kind of reveal
type of enduring but also kind of reveal
this what you refer is beautiful
and other than that well it it's already
done on that level yeah exactly the
referral is revealed by not
going into going towards it or shunning
it away trying to get rid of it to
replace it that's already The Divided
picture you haven't jumped into it hey
wait the train is there watching me he
wants to see am I seeking the central
object to my nostril watching meditation
do I just expect pleasure to Obama or am
I actually forsake in that direction and
I'm just aware of him watching me
and that's my meditation
we spoke about it before actually if you
want to practice any degree of right
mind you have to unfocus from what
you're being absorbed with just in in
colloquial terms and this is even more
so
because you're trying to discern that
mind that's kind of elusive and
generally invisible to you certainly in
the beginning
you're paid with it you're identified
with it because you're not seeing it
by learning how to sit you get to see it
as in a risen phenomenon that cannot be
yours even if you want it
you know try and you know figure out how
to discern where is it the trainer
it's by Naturally by you know refraining
from being so focused on this hay or
source of pleasure that kind of
naturally reveals itself on the right
level you don't need to and that's where
like you said in other suitors you know
only like only once a monk has fully
understood the dangerous in reality only
then afterwards he can enter the genre
so the danger gratification Escape in
regard to Sam's Pleasures for as long as
you hope that your hope is infected with
sensuality and your practice will be too
thank you
so fully seeing the Peril the danger of
debate of the track of what's in front
not losing context in regard to it
learning how to be imperturbable and not
moved by it then
that's your genre then you can take that
further in that direction
not before
that would be okay where's my head now
I did about for a bit but where's my
hair now
where is where's the mouse I'll be
waiting for